Hello. This is 6 Minute
English from BBC Learning English.
I'm Neil and I'm Georgie.
Would you like a cup of tea, Neil?
Oh, yes thanks Georgie, with milk
and three sugars, please.
Three sugars, wow!
You really have a sweet tooth -
you like eating sweet things.
Aren't you worried about your weight?
Yes, but I can't say no to sugar.
Just as our addiction to oil
is causing a climate emergency,
our addiction to sugar
is causing a health emergency
for our bodies. Sugar gives us an
instant hit at the chemical hormone
dopamine making us feel good,
but in the long run causing obesity,
tooth decay and diseases like diabetes.
But how did our addiction
to the sweet stuff begin?
That's what we'll be discussing
in this programme.
And as usual,
we'll be learning
some useful new vocabulary as well.
Anyway, here's your tea, Neil.
I just put one sugar.
Thanks, Georgie,
I'll give it a try.
Now, before we go on,
I have a question for you. Sugar cane,
which grows naturally in Asia, Africa
and the Americas first came
to England in the 11th century.
Back then it was an expensive luxury
item affordable only to kings, queens
and the very rich.
So, which English monarch loved eating
sugar so much their teeth turned black?
Was it a) King Henry VIII b)
Queen Elizabeth I
or c) Mary Queen of Scots?
I know Henry VIII was very unhealthy
so I'll guess it's him.
OK, Georgie. We'll find out
the answer later in the programme.
Just now, I compared sugar to oil as
the world's most important commodity -
a commodity is a product or
natural resource that can be traded,
bought and sold. Today,
economies, governments and wars
are based on controlling oil,
but in earlier centuries,
the same was true of sugar.
For 400 years sugar,
along with coffee and tobacco,
was grown in slavery plantations
and shipped across the
Atlantic Ocean to Europe.
By the time slavery
was ended in 1834,
the demand for sugar in Europe and
the United States was at a record high.
Here's Professor
of international history Ulbe Bosma
explaining more to BBC Radio 4
programme 'Thinking Allowed':
Sugar was already an extremely
important commodity
in the 16th and 17th and 18th century,
and in the 19th century
we see a staggering growth of sugar
consumption in Europe and United States
and so with that sugar became
the fuel for human bodies whereas
oil became the fuel for vehicles
in the 20th century.
Professor Bosma talks
about the staggering growth
in the popularity of sugar.
The adjective 'staggering'
means shocking or surprising. Just
like oil became the fuel for machine
engines, sugar became the fuel
for the human body.
Fuel is a substance that is burned
to provide heat or power
Trading companies had become rich
selling sugar grown using slave labour.
When people began to realise
the health problems of sugar
in the 20th century,
these companies needed
new ways to sell their product
and began using sugar in food
which had previously contained none,
food like bread, cereal and yoghurt.
Here's Professor Bosma again,
taking up the story for BBC
Radio 4's 'Thinking Allowed'.
You can flood the market with a certain
commodity, with sugar in this case,
but that still does not mean that
people will consume it.
So the eating habits
of people had to change. People
until the early 19th century,
they had a few spoons of sugar per week,
but not a kilo, which people consume
today in many countries in the world.
Sugar companies flooded
the market with their commodity.
If you flood the market,
you make a lot of your product available
for sale, often at a low price.
But just because something is cheap
and easily available, doesn't mean
people will eat it. So, sugar
companies tried
to increase sugar consumption
by changing people's eating habits -
the way a group of people eat,
for example, which types of food
they eat, how much of it,
and how often.
Instead of one or two spoons
of sugar per week,
people started eating kilos, with results
we see around us every day - worldwide
obesity and heart disease
have tripled in the last 50 years.
What's more because
sugary food is cheaper,
it's often the poorest in society
who are worst affected.
Hmm, maybe it's time to try having
your tea without any sugar
eh, Neil? And to reveal the answer
to your question:
which English monarch's famous love
of sugar turned their teeth black?
I guessed it was the
notorious overeater, Henry VIII.
Which was the wrong answer.
I'm afraid, Georgie.
In fact, during the years
before toothpaste and dentists,
those black stumpy teeth belonged
to Queen Elizabeth I.
OK, let's recap the vocabulary
we've learned from this programme
about sugar, starting
with 'a sweet tooth' - a fondness for
eating sweet, sugary food and drinks.
A commodity is a product or
natural resource that can be traded,
bought and sold.
Fuel is a substance such as oil or coal
that is burned
to provide heat or power.
The adjective 'staggering' means
very shocking and surprising.
If a company floods the market,
they release a lot
of a particular product for sale,
often at a low price.
And finally, eating habits
describe the way
a particular group of people eat,
for example, which types of food
they eat, how much
and how often.
Once again, our six minutes are up.
Join us again soon
for more trending topics and
useful vocabulary here at
6 Minute English. Goodbye for now!
Bye!